Welcome back.
And welcome basically. Um.
Some extent to the last class of this
course, so first of all.
So Wednesday, not class, Thursday,
yes class.
But basically we conclude today in terms
of the course itself and yesterday
evening I spoke with.
And we agreed that, I mean, it's OK,
we're covering what we intended to cover
and and so on next Thursday.
We will be dedicated to illustrate the
projects,
answer the questions about the exam
another.
Useful information because we didn't talk
about much about this aspect.
Then we agreed that we,
your legs will not.
Be strictly the date of the exam.
So that is the session.
We will give you an agenda with slot of
one hour so that you can pick up one slot.
And we're flexible on on on this part.
So when you are ready,
you did your project,
we will give you some instructions about
the submission because of course we need.
Sometime a little bit of time to evaluate,
so you will get a deadline to submit the
project and then eventually maybe other
deadlines say if you miss the first.
Mm-hmm. The uh,
the other uh is negotiable.
I mean we can have uh.
On discussion we are allocating one hour
per student,
so it will be sparse in the between
January and February and OK,
I mean it it will be me and.
Asking questions and you try to answer
after this. OK,
so that's for the organizational part.
So on Monday we are exercising
co-generation yesterday.
Code analysis. Today we do the last part,
which is feature exploration. OK.
Which means either a language.
Initially I thought about TypeScript.
But then I thought that I didn't promise
you to talk more about and so I thought
that it will be interesting to study the
binary object model components.
Uh.
Typical of the 90s and the second-half of
the 90s that were basically that still
are at least for com inside the system
that we use every day.
And so I think it's interesting to
understand from a language.
Perspective and the architecture, OK.
So so that basically an assignment
potential assignment will be find.
Describe the calling for the component
model technologies,
the semantics and all the relevant
aspects in terms of PROGRAMMING and
metaprogramming.
They these these multi language systems,
OK specification.
So it's interesting because it is a a
technology especially common that was
based on C++ in many ways.
And so it was about the layout of memory
of V tables,
mostly to expose services in a binary
form instead of search form.
OK was the way Microsoft introduced it to
have interoperability among binary.
Binary components in the open source
world.
At some point a popular alternative came
up that was called Bonobo.
And as I already mentioned,
the Mozilla Foundation adopted a
simplified version of the common standard
for the plugin model for Firefox,
but now plugins deprecated.
That's history.
Of computing and PROGRAMMING languages.
So let let's start trying to pose the
question and then again I will try to
involve you. So I am.
Working.
To my assignment for ADVANCED programming.
Course.
I need to describe and understand.
From a language, a PROGRAMMING language.
Language.
And calm technologies.
So to avoid the effect that we had
yesterday, we closed,
it may be useful to say, OK,
I will ask you.
Questions and you.
We'll answer.
We.
Paragraph information that I will use to
compose my project.
OK,
so in this way basically we're saying
don't generate 10 pages ahead of time.
But.
So.
As you can see now,
I didn't get an attempt of submission
only before we begin.
Here are two guiding principle will
follow PROGRAMMING language focus.
I will emphasize interface definition
mechanism, type systems, bind the models,
runtime semantics,
memory and object lifecycle management.
But as you can see already I'm getting
useful information.
Around the development aspects and then
assignment ready paragraph to be copy
paste. OK, first question,
what is the first question you will ask
when you have to find find about CORBA
and COM technologies?
Hmm.
First of all, I will say, uh,
give me a short introduction about CORBA.
I mean, I doubt that you are the,
you know, car bar. So I mean.
By the way,
it's an acronym which stands for Common
Object Uh.
We are runtime broker architecture.
Request. Sorry,
Broker architecture is a middleware
standard developed by the Object
Management Group to enable communication
between software components written in
different PROGRAMMING languages and
running on heterogeneous platforms.
From a PROGRAMMING language perspective,
Corpa provides a language neutral
abstraction,
language neutral abstraction of
distributed objects through the interface
definition language IDL.
IDL was really popular,
a statically typed specification language
that compiles into language specific
stops and skeleton.
These generated bindings allow developers
to invoke methods on remote object as if
they were local with the underlying
object request broker and doing
serialization, network transport,
object activation and lifecycle
management.
Corbus design reflects the 19th vision of
distributed object system,
strong timing across network boundaries,
explicit interface contracts and
standardized runtime services such as
naming, transactions and security.
That they meant to make distributed
programming resemble conventional object
oriented development OK.
OK now.
Then we got this book like definition.
Bot nest.
Before moving to COM,
I think that there should be a couple of
question that should be part of this
CORBA related part.
Sorry?
So yes, but syntax of what?
Because basically we just learned that
Corba generates something that is called
stub and skeleton according to the.
IDL specification.
So this means that I can ask for an
example of usage in Java or C or C or
Pascal or whatever and I will get some
Pascal or C or C or Java.
Call the.
So if I may suggest you,
when you start digging into new features,
don't be shy and ask for those things
that you don't know.
I mean, what are stubs?
And um.
And.
First of all, I mean,
you know what are stubs and skeleton?
I know because I am old enough to have
implemented them,
but basically I I doubt that you know
what a skeleton is or a stub is.
OK, yes,
if you think to the meaning of stub,
the stub is a sort of placeholder.
And the skeleton is the structure that
you have to feel in in in IT in computer
science.
So basically the stab refers the fact
that you want to be able to invoke a
local object as if it was implemented in
my process, but actually.
Stop is responsible for serializing.
This is what the text says.
The the the parameters for the invoking
the code to serialize it into some form
that the receiver is able to deserialize
the.
Pass to the skeleton that in the meantime
you use it to implement the service and
then the result will follow the opposite
path and the people has the impression of
the calling a local method,
but you in fact invoke the a remote
object.
OK, uh.
Can you?
Help me understand stub and skeletons and
ideal because another thing that is
interesting from a programming language.
Perspective is.
That we have a language which is called
interface definition language which is a
statically type specification language.
So I mean this is relevant to the our
discussion. What it is,
what are what is the semantics of this
thing,
how things are defined in this in this?
It's like language. Sorry, excuse me.
So the IDL is the foundation.
Oh,
the enables language independent
integrality.
Remember when we discussed about XML
schema, IDL is a precursor.
Basically it is a way to define types and
these types should be portable across
multiple languages, so.
Every language typically defines a
mapping between the types defined in the
IDL and the types in the language.
And uh.
And this formal language is is the core
because is it defines the contracts.
So you express the contracts of your API.
So IDL is a statically typed and we know
what it means declarative language.
So it means declarative.
Language.
I don't think we explicitly mentioned it,
but basically it's a language which has
no dynamic semantics and there is no
execution.
It's only use it to declare something
without any comments or statements or
something.
Usually solid solely for specifying the
structure of remote interface,
operation parameters,
exception and user defined type.
So it is like a place where you can
define type system and.
Service uh signatures,
so return value arguments and name of the.
Because AVL is not tied to any
programming language,
it seems is intentionally minimal and
similar to C++.
And the reason was because back then C++
was the most popular programming language
and so clearly you use this.
The generated stub is the client side
proxy that exposed the IDL defined
methods as if they were regular local
methods in the target programming
language.
When I.
Client in moves an operation on the stub.
The stab is responsible for marshaling
the method parameters into the
standardized combat Y format.
So basically the serialization process is
governed by a standard and the binary
representation of objects is standard.
So there is a well defined procedure to
take, I don't know, a tree,
generate a sequence of bytes that
represents that particular tree memory,
and then on the other side you revert the
process and you get back an in memory
tree.
Possibly in a different programming
language.
OK,
the skeleton is the service side
counterpart of the stub.
It receive incoming requests from the
object request broker.
So you need some runtime on your machine
that is listening on the network for
request, allocates the objects and then.
Parse the request,
invoke your skeleton and sends back the
results. OK,
this is typically the the way it works.
OK, can you generate?
A simple example.
In the add operation. So at some point,
as your colleague was suggesting,
you'd like to see something apart from
text. OK, so.
We.
So as you can see the IDL.
As ACC C++ like syntax with just the
signature of things.
So it also recalls Java,
which ultimately is inspired by C++
syntax.
So there is an interface because it's a
declarative language.
Typically you don't have.
Passes because there is no implementation,
so everything is an interface with the
signature and the calculator interface
has another operation that takes an input
to all arguments.
Because you know that in programming
languages you can pass by ref or by value
or by name or by many other ways
arguments. So if you pass by reference,
the function is able or the method is
able to alter the external value.
So in general,
when you marshal data across the network,
pass by reference is not a good idea
because you don't have anymore the
reference.
And in actually arguments can be
annotated, say OK,
this is an input parameter of this method.
Also output parameter that basically are
copied back to the caller with a new
value that will be received by the caller.
OK, so this is an example of IDL file.
And this is an example.
Conceptually, so not not fully,
but basically gives you the idea.
The stub inherits from calculator.
It implements the add method.
Function and basically.
Its implementation is.
Create a request to the object request
broker.
Create a request object with the
arguments to be marshalled.
Invoke the request.
Get the result, return the result. OK,
so this is the typical in
interoperability among processes.
Even today with HTML we're doing this.
I mean you take an object,
you generate the JSON, you send the JSON.
On the other side, JSON is parsed.
Back you want me to add the Jason,
you send the Jason in return and that's
it. Same idea, OK?
And this is the stub.
So the stub basically is I create an
instance of the stub and then I say dot
add.
I have the impression that the add method
will be executed in inside my process,
but in fact.
I I'm invoking the request on the object
request broker and and and invoke a
remote service the skeleton.
Uh in uh pseudo uh code is basically the
uh.
The code that is that can be generated,
which eventually calls your
implementation of the other function. OK,
so basically you receive a request,
you deserialize the arguments.
You compute the you invoke local
implementation.
You send back the result OK.
And the implementation is simply
something that implements A calculator
and overrides the function by saying a AB
is AA plus B. That's it.
So typically the skeleton was generated
from the IDL.
And you were responsible for implementing
just the service, the servant.
OK,
that was basically the core architecture.
Next question.
I think that there there can be at least
one more question on the Corpus side
before moving to to calm, of course.
OK, we can um.
There were official implementations of
CORBA.
The question because it's cross language.
So there were um.
Uh, implementation.
With several object requests broken,
but both commercial and open.
And it was fairly big. I mean,
for many years,
everyone was saying that that was the
future, so.
OK,
another question I I will hint I do you
think we asked all the interesting
questions to the IDL language?
IDL we said it's declarative language to
specify interface and types.
So we got an example of the interface.
What do you think will be interesting now
to to learn?
Which types you can create and define
because the expressivity of the IDL will
be crucial because it can make easy or
difficult to implement support.
On a particular programming language,
if you pick up, for instance, a union.
You know union type in in C.
Yes or no? OK,
e-mail types are available in Java.
No union in Java is implemented through
inheritance or interfaces.
So now if the IDL supports for union,
then I have to struggle in Java to
implement it. So it's relevant the typing,
the type definition language in IDL
because it may determine situation in
which the mapping is not easy.
From one language to the other.
So let's ask.
What are so a good advanced programming
course question will be what are the type
constructors?
Available in IDL.
Right,
because type constructors we learned are
basically those constructs that allows
you to create new types starting from
existing types to combine them.
OK.
Basic types as it is in any type system.
Straza.
Like C records unions enums.
And modules use it as namespaces.
So can you you generate an IDL definition
of?
Student object.
So.
In the university module there is a an
animation which is status enrolled,
suspended or graduated.
Yes.
Hmm.
No, I don't get you. Sorry.
I said that it's uh, you know, yeah.
The enumeration, yeah.
Then there is this student record is a
structure.
A structure is basically the sequence of
fields.
Each one with its type.
From this example you can also learn that
there are sequences,
so you can express lists arrays.
And then the interface students student
allows you to get a student record,
updated status,
enroll in a course and list courses of
that student. OK, so basically.
This interface student is like the class
student. It is not students,
it's just one student.
Then another interface may give you the
reference to the student class of
interface so that you can invoke its
services.
Right.
And so we got some help, right?
So by now if I if I were doing the
assignment,
probably I would have spent more time you
know in asking for examples maybe can you
tell me a place where it's it's been used
so that I can look and go and look and
etcetera, but I mean.
We have finished time,
so we have to simplify the process, OK.
Uh, now.
Let's ask her. Can you now describe calm?
Unlike CORBA,
which relies on a language neutral IDL,
COM is fundamentally a binary standard.
It defines how objects must layout their
method tables in memory. So basically.
The key names are uh.
Binary and method tables. OK,
so basically the two were different
because Microsoft was a more technical
specification than Corpa.
Even though at some point even Microsoft
adopted the IDL.
This, for instance,
is a paragraph that I would have probably
questioned during verification.
But now we got the most interesting parts.
From a programming language perspective,
COM is easily grounded in the interface
polymorphism. Nice. We know what it means.
Binary compatibility and lifetime
management. So interface polymorphism,
first key question element,
binary compatibility,
second key element and lifetime
management, memory management.
Third pillar.
The fundamental interface is called I
unknown.
It defines 3 methods that will all come.
It's like object. I unknown.
I unknown is called I unknown because
when you get the pointer to that
interface,
you don't know basically anything about
that language.
Uh, that that component, so unknown.
And the methods that must be implemented
by any common object includes query
interface.
So I can ask what what can you do for me?
I mean you object,
I have your unknown pointer.
We need to know which interface you are
implemented so they can invoke your
services. OK,
so it's a form of reflection if you want
OK.
And address release.
Hmm, which is?
Hmm yes, but if you see two methods,
address and release.
Reference counting.
Whenever you copy the reference into your
code to an object, you call that ref,
increment the counter,
and whenever you stop using a pointer,
you call release and so the counter if
the counter is good.
Back to zero,
you can reallocate the component.
These methods form the minimal runtime
contractor OK.
Now there are, I mean.
You can think a world like Bluetooth in
which the Bluetooth interfaces are well
defined. There is a specification,
there is a car interface,
headset interface with all the methods
that you have to implement.
By the way,
also Bluetooth started during those days,
so.
It is it recall resembles both CORBA and
common in the way it has been implemented.
So in Bluetooth you got a device.
The device supports a number of
interfaces.
Every interface provides functionalities.
Which is basically a common object and
and we all know that sometimes you'd like
to be to attach these to, I don't know,
JavaScript or to Visual Basic back then,
so to our uninterpreted language.
They would like to use any object without,
you know, bothering about types.
That is something that would like to.
And so basically an interface called IDs
batch was introduced so that you can.
Basically interpret the method calls by
using strings. That was basically.
And and in this way,
even the interpreted language were able
to consume com objects without having to
be compiled as it was for standard C++
implementation.
And of course,
at some point the distributed COM was
introduced to implement distributed
systems.
Sorry, I don't know who is.
OK.
Next one.
Show me AC plus plus example.
So.
This is an example which actually
overlooks the class ID.
So the fact that the registry was the
operating system data structure to
support the COM interface so that the
registry of binary components is
available into the Windows registry.
And the original Windows registry was
invented to support this,
and then it became the mess that it is
today.
So.
Typically you implement uh uh uh you
include the the header file with the
definition of the uh unknown.
You define a GUID,
which is the unique identifier that you
can generate, and it's unique,
very likely unique worldwide.
And then your interface I calculator
inherits from I unknown and it has three
arguments add.
Two arguments are used as a in input
parameters and the last argument is used
as a return. Why?
Because in this world they decided that
the return of a COM service is an.
Handle H result a number which is the
handle to a result which may be OK
success or a bunch of error.
I'm pretty sure that you've seen if you
use it Windows H result in some error.
So when you get Windows complaining about
something,
there is H result is and a number.
That number is the code of the error
basically,
and it's has been returned by the
invocation to the COM object.
And this standard call.
Remember that the calling convention is
not unique,
so you have to decide in which order you
will load parameters and who is loading
the stack and who is unloading the stack.
Standard code refers that the calling
convention when you invoke this add
function is that it is the callee,
not the caller which unloads the stack.
So.
The caller loads the stack.
The callee unloads the stack.
Basically,
it's impossible to have variable
arguments functions in this way,
because we said that in C variable
arguments requires that it's the caller
which unloads the stack at the return.
OK.
Now you can implement.
So you create a calculator which
implements the I calculator interface.
You have a.
A ref count, a reference count,
and then you increment the reference
count if.
The release decrease the reference count
and if it's zero, you delete this object,
you can free the object.
Uh,
and of course the add method simply
performs the add the query interface.
Uh, simply says OK.
If you ask for the ID of the interface
unknown or the ID of the interface
calculator.
Later.
OK, you you can say it's me.
You return the pointer to the interface,
otherwise error.
There is no interface implemented.
If you ask for an interface which is not
implemented, you return.
No interface.
You are asking me for something I don't
know how to do.
So.
How you use it? You create the component.
Uh.
You query the interface of the calculator
which is uh implementing I unknown.
So you have you know that you can invoke
a query interface, so you pass the ID.
You get.
The I calculator pointer into the
variable.
And then you invoke the service and you
release the object,
the interface and also the object. OK.
O.
Now we learn that these.
Uh.
Is.
The specific the basic of a con
specification.
We also just learned that there is this.
Can you tell me more about the?
Lus ID.
So COM runtime uses the class ID to
resolve how and where a component should
be instantiated.
And so in the open typically operating
system implementation it is you ask for
the Co creating instance to create an
object and then you get the pointer.
OK.
This is an example class definition.
What about types?
I knew that IDL was available.
Come.
Yes, COM as an IDL,
but its role and semantics differ
significantly from COBBA.
Huh.
And so you learn something.
The COMDL is a metadata specification
language.
That complements cons binary layout rules,
but does not define the model,
the object model itself.
So in basically in com you can avoid to
have IDL,
whereas in core by was mandatory to have
the IDL.
And in fact in Windows there was a binary
format which is called type libraries DLB
that you still find in Windows
implementation which contain the binary
definition of the types of a component.
So that you you have the student type and
so if you have an interface which returns
the student type,
you know how the student type should be
should be defined.
B.
Um.
The natural question would be let's
compare IDL and Microsoft IDL.
Here you get something OK.
Now that we learn that much,
what would be your next question?
Do you think you understand fully the
memory management because you know that
COM is using reference counting?
What is V?
How can we ask for checking the full
lifetime of an object? What is the?
Lifetime.
Cycle.
So Long story short, uh.
Basically you use the corporate instance
which invokes the components class
factory.
So basically all these binary components
were compiled down to either an
executable file or a DLL file.
Inside the DLL they were standard entry
points. One of these was the factory,
which is the component which is
responsible to create new objects.
And the class factory creates the
instance of the interface you're asking
for. That's where.
And then this counting performs the
memory management.
We don't the new defense.
So for instance,
the programmer to avoid to pay the cost
of the reference counting may sleep
because I know it's just now, etcetera,
and typically that was one of the most
common programming.
Those days,
because people didn't call a draft to say
the few cycles of computation,
and then suddenly the object was disposed
and you got some banging records.
And they are your problem was.
The simple are references that we learned
that are a problem with reference
counting. OK, so these were there now.
Another aspect that will be interesting
is you said that.
Comma is about.
Find a representation of.
Memory layouts.
Can you show me?
An example of memory layout of different
interfaces.
Mhm.
OK.
There we are. I was, uh, looking for this.
So typically you have a pointer.
To the I unknown because everything is an
interface and because of C++ standard,
C++ standards typically layouts pointers.
To, uh, in case of vitron methods,
but point to the methods into the virtual
table,
which is a data structure that if you
remember the.net is part of the EE class.
OK, it's the implementation, so.
If we add the pointer,
we have basically the pointer to the base
of these three fields object,
which contains the pointers to the
methods.
So if I want to invoke the address,
in fact I'm simply jumping.
To the pointer address,
the address pointer address has no
arguments apart from the this.
So you have to load the this point of
this pointer onto the stack that I invoke
that ref.
Padre will be executive in that.
You respected the the memory layout.
When you loaded the stack,
you unload this. Let's see.
You invoke the other net code and you
your program was written in C++. It works.
Release the same story.
So now if I have an object which
implements a.
Two interfaces,
in this case I log and I calculator.
In this case you will have simply the
metal tables just ordered together.
So I am on and then.
I log, I calculator and I log. OK,
so if you at the point at the point that
points to the I unknown through the
unknown,
you say OK I I want the I log and then I
will get the pointer.
Do this.
And then this will point to the table of
methods of I log.
If I ask for a calculator,
I get a different pointer to the base
address where I find the.
Uh, the thing and so.
Each interface will have.
The I unknown methods plus the interface
methods and who cares?
Because at the end of the day these are
just pointers to functions.
They are not implementation,
so you can replicate the interface
without damaging the type system.
So conceptually the.
I calculator and I log both implements.
I am known and we know that in case of
multiple inheritance this would be a
diamond and a problem,
but without state we have no problem.
Because there is no shared state to take
care about and so basically you use.
You can replicate the the fields without
any problem and the system and the
semantics will keep working without any
problem.
Typically the query interface with will
be the same point to the same method
because in the class I will have only one.
Web interface implementation or other F
release implementation.
OK, as you can see here.
You get uh uh few examples.
Why this matters to for language
interoperability?
Because every interface pointer just is
just a pointer to V table pointers.
OK.
What will be another question?
Oh, by the way, historical not this not.
One of the early names of.
net runtime of the CLR was core COR.
If you look at the source code,
you still find traces about this early
name and core.
Core was stood for back then to be common
object runtime. OK,
so net was originally conceived as a
basically as a way to implement
components inside Windows.
Using a common object runtime with same
type definitions, etcetera.
So before moving into the natural
comparison between core by cone.
Uh.
Um.
What? Uh.
Ecom introduces.
In COM because I mean I skip it,
but basically COM was just the in process
component creation or out of process.
So basically also in COM you can have a
stub and a skeleton.
And at some point, I think it was 97,
Microsoft introduced DCOM,
which was a distributed component object
model like CORBA, OK.
So DCOM extends the component object
model from a local in process component
system to a fully distributed
architecture. OK,
so a component is not anymore inside the
process,
can be outside into another process or
even on a on into a a different machine.
This complicates memory management
because if you release a common component
you see the and you feel the memory,
but if the call is hosted by a different
process, possibly.
I have to terminate the frost because
it's not needed anymore. OK,
so the DECOM specification introduces a
lot of challenges,
especially in the network communications,
because if you are referring to an object
which is running on a different machine.
Then it's complicated because you don't
know whether if your caller stop it to to
work and so I so I have machine A with
the service.
Machine A asked to machine BA component.
The component is allocated in machine B
machine B.
A machine A dies and you have garbage in
machine B because nobody knows that that
component will not be referred to anyone
by anyone. OK,
that is basically the situation and.
Oh.
And basically they started doing a little
bit of ping inside the net. OK,
so machine A was pinging machine B.
Are you still there? And vice versa.
And this seemed a good idea, but then.
It didn't really scale up well.
If you were allocating doses of hundreds
or thousands of components,
you may end up separating the bandwidth
because of this thing.
So that was a problem, OK.
Can you compare?
Uh.
Call BA and calm.
So as you can see the original prompt
that say I need to do an assignment
influence the all the remaining statement.
Please.
Generate a table with differences.
So basically the idea was use it the only
to define structured type by Microsoft,
not the full interfaces.
Names in CORBA for interface GUID based.
Uh, for com and so on and so forth, OK.
Uh.
So one of the success of COM,
I think it was the way Microsoft made
office evolve because COM was introduced.
Let me ask just for.
Uh.
I heard that COM was introduced to
implement.
Orly.
Have you ever heard OLE Ole?
Because sometimes you may have seen on
Windows Ole 32 DLL crashing.
So all it was.
This idea that in the 90s was very
revolutionary of object linking and embed.
So you will know that you can insert into
more than acceptable.
Or analogy.com.
I mean,
I guess you eventually end up doing this
kind of things.
This is basically possible because I mean,
of course you may assume that as it
happens in open office.
Everything is compiled in Django,
more than Excel equivalence can
interoperate because they've been
compiled together. OK, so that's OK.
They need something if insert the Excel.
OK.
But when in Office you were able to
include the Adobe PDF documents inside a
Word file.
Adobe Acrobat was a different program
developed by a different company.
It might have been the the source files.
So basically the idea was OK,
let's define a set of interfaces by which
I can create allocate a component,
then there are interfaces that I can
invoke.
To get.
Generate the view, load the file,
the data is here, etcetera.
So that I can generate a small window
that shows the rendering of the etcetera.
OK,
that that was basically the object
thinking and embedding technology and it
was quite revolutionary in office
information because.
It opened up the ability to mix and match
data coming from different sources with
programs implemented by different vendors,
and so that was one of the.
Original healer applications that made a
call popular so.
Word is a common component that can be
embedded in cell or vice versa.
Word was used as an editor in Outlook.
Outlook was a program.
Word was a different program and the two
were able to share some pictures on the
screen and cooperate together.
OK, nice. At some point myself started to.
net.
So they implemented the very same comp by
layouts in dotnet.
And silently replaced the the the core
component definition of C++ components
with.
net counterparts and so they made the
migrate from C++ binary object code to.
net runtime.
Intermediate language code in a
transpiring way.
That was quite significantly as an
engineering lead.
And in fact,
the name for components that were able to
displace graphics was known as Active X.
You may have heard of or seen some error
message about Active X components failing
to load or something like that.
Pretty common, OK.
I will probably conclude.
This enquiry,
an investigation with what are Bom Corb
counterpart?
These.
OK,
I mean clearly COM and CORBA address a
well defined problem,
the ability to invoke remote components
now that they are not basically used
anymore. I mean they still inside windows,
but this is just legacy, but basically.
They're gone. What are the alternatives?
Because we it's still interesting to be
able to invoke remote object services.
And basically the trace was binary
interoperability,
cross language interoperability.
So.net is an alternative.
It defines types.
It allows you to combine classes like
very much like Java.
Windows Runtime.
Which basically.
Uh is inspired from com.
They have thrown away a bunch of legacy
stuff.
And it's usually Windows 1011.
So basically the con components
architecture is still underneath some
some somehow.
Uh.
And there are bindings for C++, C#,
Rust and JavaScript. That's interesting.
Webassembly component model.
We discussed it already.
The Webassembly we we did some,
but we didn't discover this aspect which
has some.
Similar points to that you share with
between Webassembly and COM and GRCP for
internal microservices which is an open
standard GRPC.
From Google is also similar to CORBA and
distributed object system and for
distributed object system I would have
said yes, REST is the real.
Heritage of the the Corba platform.
The rest is basically this approach in
which you.
Use URLs to define object structures,
verbs to define operations and.
HTT as a transport rotocol.
Grahql.
Meta launch the the Grahql standard.
Apache 3 and Arrow,
which basically focus on serialization.
Message brokers, Kafka, Rabi, QMQ,
Nets are all these are basically
specialized version of distributed
objects in which basically you have
queues of objects with ties,
but basically it's the same thing.
And of course cloud native microservices.
Why?
First, binary, uh, fragility.
Specially calm.
In CORBA complexity was complicated and
distributed objects were never
transparent.
So you wrote an application with the stub
and you were convinced that you were
invoking a local method and then the
application crashes because the remote
server was out.
That was terrible. OK,
vendor looking for Microsoft.
Deployment was not easy.
The versioning was complicated to
maintain, so I I would agree. OK,
now I got all this information.
I read the information,
I decide which questions were made sense,
etcetera.
Now I'm ready.
It was several part of my project.
I joined together the the text.
I assured that the final result is a
readable project. I mean so.
I may even have to review a little bit
the English so that it looks like a
single document.
I may ask the I can you please fix that.
It's OK. I am the processor.
That you have to submit the and now
unlike with one big problem,
how can get convinced that all this
information is true?
Double check. Double check. I mean.
Yes, in principle you can, uh,
ask your builder uh.
But honestly,
I wouldn't trust too much this approach
because there is some risk that both are
losing anything and you're submitting the
better. I mean,
you can get a first impression out of
this book and please check this and get.
Feedback,
but probably I will also Google for some,
I don't know, core by example,
for instance to check whether the idea
examples make sense.
Or if there are similar examples that or
better examples,
I can go and check for the idea
specification and have a quick read to be
sure that the unions are allowed or not
or any of the information.
That they are reported. OK,
so the verification in my opinion will
take you more time than the than the
generation because we will go through
your submissions.
And I mean, of course.
We will review,
but not with the spirit of giving a grade
the project.
We will review how you did the do the
check and of course if it's insufficient,
you took the risk of getting false
information out.
Of your submission and you are
responsible for it because in all the
legal framework of the AI,
whether it's documents or programs or any
other.
Artifactor.
If you submit something generated by the
I,
you're taking responsibility for the
content. This is what the law.
132 of 2025 in this country states.
So if you submit some information
generated code through AAI,
you're responsible for it.
And so you will get beautiful questions
during your exams in that case,
which is our implementation of taking
responsibility of the verification. OK,
so please try to do your best.
To double check the information,
which means that find the relevant part
of the generated text that you think they
are relevant and in the verification
document say OK,
I did check this because I think it's
relevant.
I need check that because I think it's
read out.
I googled and found that this is impact
is true. I found a lot of information.
I found the corpus specification.
I mean there are.
Multiple potential answer,
but please find the rule. Don't get.
Don't think that if you double check with
another AI,
that's enough because it's not OK.
There is some risk that you're passing
through the common relevant information.
It is an easy way to get your first
impression.
You can get some help with where to focus,
yes,
but don't feel that that is the only
available option on the table.
Any comments or questions?
So I don't know if it's my flu or the
light or whatever you sounds like type
and perhaps you also have the right to.
So I think.
If there are no comments,
we can stop early.
That was the final example of a final
project.
You will get the least of projects.
I forgot a few things to stress first.
Project is individual.
You are allowed to discuss,
but eventually you have to submit an
individual project.
Second,
I don't know how many project will we
will publish.
For sure more than 20,
but I'm not sure we will be able to
produce 70 or 80 projects as the number
as the students declared to be interested
in this course on the Antarctica, so.
Of course.
Two students may.
Do the same project because we are lucky.
Because this project will be somehow
under specified. OK,
because I mean then I think that you
should say OK,
I have to take on this problem.
I want to focus on this and I think that
that.
Is for the game,
so you will have some freedom on.
I will try to give you some direction,
but you may say OK yes,
but I focus on this because otherwise it
will be to be as an assignment.
And it's OK.
So even if two students take the same
project,
I don't see any particular issue because
if those are equivalent project,
it's impossible and it was impossible
before AI.
We deny that both the dice even more,
it's impossible.
OK, so I mean,
I hope that you will try to do this
project for yourself and to learn things,
not just to spread the exam,
because at the end of the day, as we said,
this is just a a filter to pass students
that.
Have to perform this experience that will
believe it's important for you in the
future.
And so please take the opportunity,
not try to cheat. It's not helping anyone,
especially you.
OK.
OK. Yes, yes, I, I, I, I'm really sorry.
The the last four weeks of it has been
more than thought for me and so I'm late.
I know, sorry,
but it's a promise that I will.
It's we've been two major press prices in
the 80,
one both probably no the one engineer
engineer will be the notice,
but the last one in mid November.
Has been quite difficult to go through
and then the.
Second authentication factor is you have
no idea how many of your colleagues are
writing me personally.
I mean you're 47001 and then there are
students that said this is my mobile
number. Can you call me?
I mean,
how can you think that someone is calling
47,000 students? OK, so yes,
sorry and thanks for your patience.
Um.